Fair Employment Practices Commission Records on Microfilm 5662 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Fair Employment Practices Commission Records on Microfilm
1842-1946
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Fair Employment Practices Commission
5662 mf
23.33 cubic feet
210 microfilm reels
Records (documents), microfilm.
Office files, hearing records, employment practices files, public relations files, correspondence, closed case files and administrative files
5689586
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, January 28, 2016
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, June 06, 2019
Biographical / Historical
President Roosevelt created the Fair Employment Practices Committee (FEPC) by signing Executive Order 8802, on June 25, 1941, which stated, "there shall be no discrimination in the employment of workers in defense industries or government because of race, creed, color, or national origin." This was due to the urging of A. Philip Randolph, who was the founding president of the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters.
Roosevelt transferred the FEPC to the War Production Board and then to the War Manpower Commission with Executive Order 9040, in 1942. In response to this, FEPC Chairman MacLean accused Roosevelt's administration of reducing the FEPC to "a small Federal bureau without power," and A. Phillip Randolph said that the White House was pursuing a policy that was completely "emasculating" the usefulness of the committee.
Roosevelt greatly strengthened the FEPC with a new executive order, Executive Order 9346, in 1943. It required that all government contracts have a non-discrimination clause and gave jurisdiction over government establishments.
In 1948, President Truman called for a permanent FEPC, anti-lynching legislation, and the abolition of the poll tax. A Democratic coaltion, however, prevented the legislation's passage. In 1950, the House approved a permanent FEPC bill, but Southern senators filibustered and the bill failed. Thus, Congress has never enacted the FEPC into law. A lack of permanent legislation to reinforce the FEPC and the controversy plaguing the bill inherently contributed to the FEPC's ineffective implementation. However, New York, New Jersey, Massachusetts, Connecticut and Washington successfully enacted and enforced their own FEPC laws at the state level.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3035: Eric Polisar Papers /4039: Milton R. Konvitz Papers 5235: National Consumers League Records 5307: Consumers' League of New York City Records 5480 OH: Fair Employment Practices Commission Oral History Project Audio recordings and Transcripts 5484: Railway Labor Executives' Association Records 5488 A: BRAC Chicago Files 5541: Philip Taft Papers 5582: Archives Foreign File (AFF) 5583/1: Archives Organization File (AOF) Part 1 5619: ACWA Records 5619/007: ACTWU Organizing Department Files 5648: President's Committee Report "In the Matter of a Hearing to Hear Evidence on Complaints of Racial Discrimination in Employment on Certain Railroads of the U.S." 5662 mf: Fair Employment Practices Commission Records on Microfilm 5688 mf: Binghamton Central Labor Union Records on Microfilm 5780/002: ILGWU David Dubinsky Correspondence 5780/090 P: ILGWU Central Pennsylvania District Photographs 5815 mf: Papers of the International Labor Defense on Microfilm 5918 mf: Minutes of the Executive Council of AFL, Pt. 2 on Microfilm 5976 mf: Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters Records on Microfilm 6021/005: Theodore W. Kheel Speeches and Articles 6036/024: Maida Springer Kemp Oral History Interview 6046: Archives Union File (AUF) 6047: Archives Information File
African, Americans -- Civil rights; Discrimination in employment; Defense industries -- Government policy; Defense industries -- Law and legislation; World War, 1939-1945 -- African-Americans; United States. Committee on Fair Employment Practice; Friend, Bruce I.
5689586
- Minutes And Memorandums, 1940-1946 (Reel 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Summary of minutes of meetings, January 19, 1942 - September 15, 1945. Summaries of actions taken by the Committee at its meetings, September 11, 1942 - March 15, 1943; July 6, 1943 - July 21, 1945. Agenda, August 27, 1941 - August 27, 1945. Documents file, January 15, 1944 - August 27, 1945. Office memorandums, October 1942 - January 1945. Office files of Malcolm Ross, June 1940 - June 1946 (A-L).
- Office Files of Malcom Ross, 1940-1946 (Reel 2)
  June 1940 - June 1946 (M - Missouri Pacific; also included are materials for final report which appear in proper alphabetical sequence).
- Office Files, 1940-1946 (Reel 3)
  Office files of Malcom Ross, June 1940 - June 1946 (Missouri Pacific - Z; also unarranged material). Office files of Max Berking, Assistant to the Chairman, May 1944 - October 1945. Office files of George M. Johnson, Deputy Chairman, November 1941 - October 1945 (A-M).
- Office Files of George M. Johnson, 1941-1945 (Reel 4)
  Office files of George M. Johnson, Deputy Chairman, November 1941 - October 1945 (N-Z). Requests for information concerning federal employment of Negroes, April 1-8, 1942. Office files of George M. Johnson, Director, December 1941 - November 1945 (A-G).
- Office Files of George M. Johnson, 1941-1945 (Reel 5)
  Office Files of George M. Johnson, Director, December 1941 - November 1945 (H-Telephone Company).
- Office Files, 1941-1945 (Reel 6)
  Office files of George M. Johnson, Director, December 1941 - November 1945 (Transcontinental and Western Air, Inc. -Z; also unarranged material). Office files of Emanuel H. Bloch, Hearing Examiner, July 1944 - January 1946 (A-Z; also unarranged material).
- Office Files, 1943-1946 (Reel 7)
  Office files of Maceo W. Hubbard, January 1943 - January 1946. Office files of Frank D. Reeves, Trial Attorney, December 1942 - August 1945 (A-P).
- Office Files, 1942-1945 (Reel 8)
  Office files of Frank D. Reeves, Trial Attorney, December 1942 - August 1945 (Q-Z). Office files of Evelyn M. Cooper, Trial Attorney, September 1944 - December 1945 (unarranged).
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 9)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Railroad: Transcripts. Railroad: Agreements, correspondence, and job rosters at various railroads
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 10)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Railroad: Summary, findings and directives. Railroad: Miscellaneous correspondence, reports and complaints (Part I).
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 11)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Railroad: Miscellaneous correspondence, reports and complaints (Part II). Railroad: Exhibits to hearings. Railroad: Discriminatory employment questionnaires (Part I)
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 12)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Railroad: Discriminatory employment questionnaires (Part II). Railroad: Union agreements.
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 13)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Oregon Shipbuilding Corporation; Vancouver and Swann Island Shipyards; Kaiser Shipyards of Portland; and International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Welders and Helpers of America (Boilermakers Union) Transcripts. Kaiser Shipyards, Employment statistics by Race (Part I).
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 14)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Kaiser shipyards, Employment by race (Part II). Shipbuilding: Boilermakers Union, Exhibits (Part I).
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 15)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Shipbuilding: Boilermakers Union, Exhibits (Part II). Titeflex Metal Company. Buckingham, Bruce W. Indianapolis Railway, Incorporated. Discrimination in defense training. Civil Service commissions. FEPC meeting, February 17, 1943.
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 16)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Perry, Leslie S. Western Pipe and Steel, et. al. Major, Seth v. Library of Congress. Northwest Mining and Exchange Company v. Peter Venture. Chicago public hearings of the Illinois State Commission on the Condition of Urban Colored Populations, January 3, 1941.
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 17)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Chicago public hearings of the Illinois State Commission on the Condition of Urban Colored Population, January 4, 1941. Potter, Herbert Elmer v. The United States Employees' Compensation Commission. Birmingham hearings. Hearings held before a Special Committee of the House of Representatives to investigate acts of Executive Agencies beyond the scope of their authority: January 11, 1944; February 25, 1944; March 1, 1944; March 2, 1944.
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 18)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Hearings held before a Special Committee of the House of Representatives in investigate acts of Executive Agencies beyond the scope of their authority: March 10, 1944. Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company, Window Glass Cutters League of America, Ceramic and Silica Sand Workers of America, and Paul G. Schmidt et al, Jehovah's Witnesses. Seafarers International Union of North America. Cook County Plumbers Union. Dow Chemical Company v. S. Kenneth Sterling. Complaints of Discrimination in employment in defense industries because of race, creed, color, or national origin; October 20, 1941.
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 19)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Complaints of discrimination in employment in defense industries because of race, creed, color, or national origin: October 21, 1941. Southwest (Mexicans). Sidney, Rone v. Robert H. Holt. Wagner Electric Corporation v. Ollie Haynes et al. Bussman Manufacturing Company v. Thelma Shuford et al. Carter Carburetor Corporation v. Pearl Maddox et al. Amertorp Corporation v. Lillian D. Reynolds et al.
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 20)
  December 1941 - March 1946. St. Louis Shipbuilding and Steel Company v. Samuel A. Layne et al. Philadelphia Rapid Transit Employees Union. United States Cartridge Company v. Irene Johnson et al. McQuay-Norris Manufacturing Company v. Ollie Haynes et al. McDonnell Aircraft Corporation v. Sarah J. Bundy et al. Western Cartridge Company.
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 21)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Los Angeles Railway Corporation v. Complaints of Alfonso Edwards, James H. Herod, Jr., Charles M. Robinson, Sidney L. Robinson, James E. Savoy, Nona S. Slayden, and Others. Shell Oil Company, Inc. and Oil Workers International Union, Local 367, CIO. Line Material Company. F. H. Lawson Company. Crosley Corporation.
- Records Relating to Hearings, 1941-1946 (Reel 22)
  December 1941 - March 1946. Baldwin Company. Capital Transit Company. Victor Electric Products, Inc. Kirk and Blum Manufacturing Company Cambridge Tile Manufacturing Company. United Biscuit Company of America. Schaible Company. General Cable Corporation. Texas and New Orleans Railroad Company, and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen. Goodyear Aircraft Corporation. International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffers, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America, Local 299, el al. Key System and Division 192, Amalgamated Association of Street, Electric Railway and Motor Coach Employees of America.
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 23)
  Complaints not Specifying a Particular Company: Region I (A-Z) Region III (A-R)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 24)
  Complaints not Specifying a Particular Company: Region III (S-Z); unarranged Region IV (A-F)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 25)
  Complaints not Specifying a Particular Company: Region IV (G-Z) Region VII (A-Z) Complaints Against a Particular Company: Numerous Regions (A-Z)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 26)
  Complaints Against a Particular Company: Region I (A-Z) Region IV (A-Z)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 27)
  Complaints Against a Particular Company: Region VII (A-Z)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 28)
  Complaints Against a Particular Company: Region XII (A-Z)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 29)
  Complaints Against Railroads: Numerous Regions
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 30)
  Complaints Against Government Agencies: Region I (A-Z) Region IV (A-I)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 31)
  Complaints Against Government Agencies: Region IV (J-U part I)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 32)
  Complaints Against Government Agencies: Region IV (U part II-Z; also unarranged part I)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 33)
  Complaints Against Government Agencies: Region IV (unarranged part I) Region VII (unarranged part II)
- Central Files: Fair Employment Practices (Reel 34)
  Complaints Against Government Agencies: Region VII (unarranged part II) Region XII (unarranged)
- Central Files (Reel 35)
  Fair Employment Practices: Complaints against unions; discrimination in defense training (U.S. Office of Education and Institution not within jurisdiction). Fiscal: General. General Correspondence: Letters sent on general subject matter (A-E)
- Central Files: General Correspondence (Reel 36)
  Letters sent on general subject matter (F-Z). Requests to companies to end violation of E.O. 8802 (A-Z). Also Hearings: General.
- Central Files: Hearings (Reel 37)
  Specific hearings. Summaries. Findings. Procedures.
- Central Files (Reel 38)
  Legislation. Meetings: General and FEPC. Memorandums: General, All committee members, All staff, and Regional directors and regions for specific individuals (A-P)
- Central Files: Memorandums (Reel 39)
  Regional Directors and Regions: Specific individuals (R-Z). Regions in general: Region I, Region II, Region III, Region IV.
- Central Files: Memorandums (Reel 40)
  Regional Directors and Regions: Regions in general; Region V, Region VI, Region VII, Region VIII, Region IX.
- Central Files: Memorandums (Reel 41)
  Regional Directors and Regions: Regions in general; Region X, Region XI, Region XII, Region XIII. Orders. Organization. Personnel; Job descriptions and Suggestions by employees. Policy and Procedure; General, Administrative, Correspondence, Field, Procedure manual, Fair employment practices.
- Central Files: Public Relations (Reel 42)
  Anonymous letters. Appreciation and Commendation letters. Complaints, Criticisms, Protests (letters of). Motion pictures. General correspondence (letters offering comments, etc., A-C).
- Central Files: Public Relations (Reel 43)
  General correspondence (letters offering comments, etc., D-M).
- Central Files: Public Relations (Reel 44)
  General correspondence (letters offering comments, etc., N-V).
- Central Files: Public Relations (Reel 45)
  General correspondence (letters offering comments, etc., W-Z). General Correspondence (Miscellaneous nature, A-Z).
- Central Files: Public Relations (Reel 46)
  General correspondence: "Pat on the Back" regarding individuals (A-Z) and organizations (part I).
- Central Files: Public Relations, Publications, And Reports (Reel 47)
  General correspondence: "Pat on the Back" regarding organizations (part II) and "Crack Pots". Radio Programs. Speeches. Petitions. Resolutions. Publications: General; Press releases, Committee on Fair Employment Practices; Other releases, Committee on Fair Employment Practices; Press releases (Other than the Committee); Other releases (Other than the Committee); State legislature; Requests for comment and review of articles for publication; books, booklets, and pamphlets. Reports: General (A-C).
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 48)
  General (D-Z). Fair employment practices. Report of discriminatory hiring practices (uses form 510). Company reports to and from the field.
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 49)
  Federal Employment (A-Ta).
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 50)
  Federal Employment (Te-Z). Statistical Reports. Case Reports. Progress Reports. Chronological. Weekly reports by region (master file) and bimonthly: Region I Region II
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 51)
  Weekly Reports by region (master file) and bimonthly: Region III Region IV Region V Region VI
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 52)
  Weekly Reports by region (master file) and bimonthly: Region VII Region VIII Region IX Region X Region XI Region XII: Los Angeles
- Central Files: Reports, 1944-1945 (Reel 53)
  Weekly Reports by region (master file) and bimonthly: Region XII: San Francisco Region XIII Weekly reports, chronological, June 10, 1944 - August 15, 1945.
- Central Files: Reports, 1943 (Reel 54)
  Weekly Reports, chronological, October 2, 1943 - June 3, 1943.
- Central Files: Reports, 1943 (Reel 55)
  Weekly Reports, chronological, August 14, 1943 - September 30, 1943. Monthly Statistical Reports by region (master file): Regions I-XI
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 56)
  Monthly Statistical Reports by region (master file): Region XII Region XIII Final Disposition Reports: Region I Region II (A-R)
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 57)
  Final Disposition Reports: Region II (S-Z) Region III (A-R)
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 58)
  Final Disposition Reports: Region III (S-Z) Region IV (A-Z) Region V (A-H)
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 59)
  Final Disposition Reports: Region V (I-Z) Region VI (A-Q)
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 60)
  Final Disposition Reports: Region VI (R-Z) Region VII (A-Z) Region VIII (A-Z) Region IX (A-Z) Region X (A-K)
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 61)
  Final Disposition Reports: Region X (L-Z) Region XI (A-Z) Region XII (A-Q)
- Central Files: Reports (Reel 62)
  Final Disposition Reports: Region XII (R-Z) Region XIII (A-Z) Analysis of FDR's: Regions I-XIII. Compliance Reports: Regions I-XIII.
- Central Files: Reports, Rulings, And Transcripts, 1942 (Reel 63)
  Reports: Work Stoppage Reports. Requests for Further Action (RFAs) from field. Statistical Reports by Division of Field Operations (DFO). Tension Area Reports. Rulings: Comptroller General's decisions. Transcripts: Specific transcripts, February 16, 1942 - October 26, 1942.
- Central Files: Transcripts, 1842-1943 (Reel 64)
  Specific transcripts, November 23, 1942 - December 27, 1943.
- Central Files: Transcripts And U.S. Government, 1944-1945 (Reel 65)
  Specific transcripts, January 15, 1944 - September 4, 1945. U.S. Government: Aliens in Defense, General (A-N)
- Central Files: U.S. Government (Reel 66)
  U.S. Government: Aliens in Defense, General (O-Z) and Specific Groups. Government Agencies: Specific Agencies (A-U).
- Central Files: U.S. Government (Reel 67)
  Government Agencies: Specific Agencies (W-Z) General File (A-Z)
- Office Files of John A. Davis, Director, 1941-1946 (Reel 68)
  September 1941 - April 1946 (A-R).
- Office Files, 1941-1946 (Reel 69)
  Office files of John A. Davis, Director, September 1941 - April 1946 (S-Z), also unarranged material. Office files of Marjorie M. Lawson, Assistant Director, October 1942 - October 1945 (A-L).
- Office Files, 1942-1945 (Reel 70)
  Office files of Marjorie M. Lawson, Assistant Director, October 1942 - October 1945 (M-Z). Office files of Wilfred C. Leland, Jr., Consultant, October 1943 - August 1945 (A-N). Also includes Congested Areas, Current Work, Economic Analysis, and Minority Workers which appear in proper alphabetical sequence.
- Office Files Of Wilfred C. Leland Jr., Consultant, 1943-1945 (Reel 71)
  Office files of Wilfred C. Leland Jr., Consultant, October 1943 - August 1945 (O-Z). Also includes Recommendations for policy and action, Special labor groups, and Study of industrial communities, which appear in proper alphabetical order. Additionally, unarranged miscellaneous files appear at the end of the series immediately following "Z".
- Office Files, 1943-1945 (Reel 72)
  Office files of Cornelius Golightly, Compliance Analyst, October 1943 - September 1945 (A-Z); also unarranged material. Office files of Carol Coan, Compliance Analyst, September 1943 - July 1945 (A-Z). Office files of Joy P. Davis, Compliance Analyst, September 1943 - May 1945. Unarranged through List of Public Hearings.
- Office Files and Reference File, 1941-1946 (Reel 73)
  Office files of Joy P. Davis, Compliance Analyst, September 1943 - May 1945. Unarranged from Old Reports and Office Memos. Office files of Walter L. Simmons, Clerk-Stenographer, October 1943 - August 1945. Unarranged. Reference file, July 1941 - April 1946: Publication file (A-Z) Books, periodicals, pamphlets and newspapers (part I)
- Reference File, 1941-1946 (Reel 74)
  Reference File, July 1941 - April 1946: Books, periodicals, pamphlets and newspapers (part II) Synopsis of books and periodicals (A-Z) Studies and reports Speeches and Statements (part I)
- Reference File And Records, 1941-1946 (Reel 75)
  Reference File, July 1941 - April 1946: Speeches and statements (part II) Records relating to the first report of the FEPC, March 1944 - May 1945. "Tension File", July 1943 - October 1945 (Alabama - New Mexico)
- Office Files, 1941-1946 (Reel 76)
  "Tension File", July 1943 - October 1945 (New York - Wyoming). Office files of Will Maslow, Director, September 1943 - May 1945 (unarranged). Office files of Clarence M. Mitchell, Associate Director, May 1943 - April 1946 (A-Z; also unarranged correspondence). Office files of Eugene Davidson, Assistant Director, October 1941 - April 1946 (unarranged through Exhibits and Other File Material).
- Office Files, 1941-1946 (Reel 77)
  Office files of Eugene Davidson, Assistant Director, October 1941 - April 1946 (unarranged: Statements - Miscellaneous). Office files of Ernest G. Trimble, Senior Field Representative, November 1941- November 1945 (A-Z; also unarranged material). Office files of John Beecher, Senior Field Representative, December 1941 - September 1945 (unarranged through Seventh Regional Labor Supply Committee).
- Office Files And Field Instructions/Letters, 1941-1945 (Reel 78)
  Office files of John Beecher, Senior Field Representative, December 1941 - September 1945 (unarranged: Mobile, Alabama - Coosa River Ordinance Plant). Field Instructions, August 1943 - May 1945. Field Letters, August 1943 - June 1945.
- Active Cases, 1943-1946 (Reel 80)
  June 1943 - April 1946: Regions I-IV Region V (A-K)
- Active Cases, 1943-1946 (Reel 80)
  June 1943 - April 1946: Region V (L-Z) Region VI Region VII Region VIII Region IX (A-M)
- Active Cases, 1943-1946 (Reel 81)
  June 1943 - April 1946: Region IX (N-Z) Region X Region XI
- Active Cases, 1943-1946 (Reel 82)
  June 1943 - April 1946: Region XII
- Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Reel 83)
  Correspondence Relating To Cases, December 1943 - October 1945 (A-K)
- Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Reel 84)
  Correspondence Relating To Cases, December 1943 - October 1945 (L-Se)
- Correspondence, Files, and Press Releases, 1941-1945 (Reel 85)
  Correspondence Relating To Cases, December 1943 - October 1945 (Sh-Z). Files of St. Clair Bourne, Information Officer, July 1943 - November 1945 (A-Z: also unarranged miscellaneous correspondence). Press Releases, August 1941 - November 1945 (A).
- Press Releases and Weekly News Digests, 1941-1945 (Reel 86)
  Press Releases, August 1941 - November 1945 (B-Z). Weekly News Digests, December 1943 - July 1945 (Volumes I and II).
- Region I: Active Cases (A-Z), Closed Cases (A-F) (Reel 1FR)
- Region I: Closed Cases (G-Z) (Reel 2FR)
- Region II: Correspondence (Unarranged And A-Bar) (Reel 3FR)
- Region II: Correspondence (Bas-Cu) (Reel 4FR)
- Region II: Correspondence (D-Gl) (Reel 5FR)
- Region II: Correspondence (Go-K) (Reel 6FR)
- Region II: Correspondence (Ke-Or) (Reel 7FR)
- Region II: Correspondence (P-Sn) (Reel 8FR)